### MITCHELL JONES

#### PERSONAL INFORMATION

email mfjones2@illnois.edu

website http://mfjones2.web.engr.illinois.edu

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

Low-dimensional computational and discrete geometry. Developing approximation and randomized algorithms for problems related to partitioning, classifying, and summarizing point sets [2–4, 10]. Dynamic data structures for approximating low-dimensional proximity problems [5, 9]. Previously worked on more classical combinatorial optimization problems in graph theory [11] and bioinformatics [13].

#### **EDUCATION**

2016–Present University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Fifth year Ph.D. Candidate · Degree expected August 2021

Research interests: Computational geometry, randomized & approximation algorithms,

combinatorial optimization. Advisor: Sariel Har-Peled.

2012–2015 University of Sydney, Australia

Bachelor of Computer Science and Technology (Advanced) Honors Class I and University Medal · GPA: 4.0

Thesis: The Maximum Facility Location Problem [17].

Advisor: Julián Mestre.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

Aug 2016–Present Research assistant

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Research assassint, working with Sariel Har-Peled on problems in computational geometry. Developing approximation and randomized algorithms for various optimization problems in low dimensional discrete geometry [2, 4–6, 16].

Aug 2017–Dec 2019 Teaching assistant

Univerity of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign A teaching assistant for various courses at UIUC (see below for exact courses taught). Involves teaching weekly labs, grading, office hours, and answering student questions on Piazza.

August 2019 Visiting research assistant

University of Sydney, Australia Visiting research assassint, working with Joachim Gudmundsson and students on various voting theory problems in computational geometry.

Mar 2016–Jun 2016 Research assistant

University of Sydney, Australia Research assassint, worked with Julián Mestre and other faculty on developing new approaches for computing the treewidth of a graph. Led to the publication of a paper in IPEC 2016 [8], and then Algorithmica [11].

*Jul 2013–Jun 2016* Teaching assistant

University of Sydney, Australia

A teaching assistant for various courses at the University of Sydney (see below for exact courses taught). Involved teaching weekly labs, grading, and answering student questions on Piazza.

Nov 2015–Feb 2016 Software engineering intern

Google, Australia

A software engineering internship, worked with the social & discovery team.

Nov 2014–Feb 2015 Software engineering intern

Google, Australia

A software engineering internship, worked with the Google Chrome apps team.

Nov 2013–Mar 2014 Summer research scholarship

University of Sydney, Australia

Worked with Joachim Gudmundsson on various discrete and computational geometry problems over the summer of 2013–14.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

All papers listed below can be found at <a href="http://mfjones2.web.engr.illinois.edu/">http://mfjones2.web.engr.illinois.edu/</a>. The coauthors are listed *alphabetically*.

## Conference publications

- [1] S. Har-Peled and M. Jones. *Some geometric applications of anti-chains*. *Canadian Conference on Computational Geometry (CCCG 2020)*, 1–6, 2020.
- [2] S. Har-Peled, M. Jones, and S. Rahul. *Active learning a convex body in low dimensions*. *International Colloquium on Automata, Languages and Programming (ICALP 2020)*, 64:1–64:17, 2020.
- [3] S. Har-Peled and M. Jones. *Fast algorithms for geometric consensuses*. *Symposium on Computational Geometry (SoCG 2020)*, 50:1–50:16, 2020.
- [4] S. Har-Peled and M. Jones. *Journey to the center of the point set*. *Symposium on Computational Geometry (SoCG 2019)*, To appear in ACM Transactions on Algorithms (TALG). 41:1–41:14, 2019.
- [5] T. M. Chan, S. Har-Peled, and M. Jones. *On locality-sensitive orderings and their applications*. *Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science Conference (ITCS 2019)*, 21:1–21:17, 2019.
- [6] S. Har-Peled and M. Jones. *On separating points by lines*. *Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA 2018)*, 918–932, 2018.
- [7] M. Jones, J. Mestre, and B. Scholz. *Towards memory-optimal schedules for SDF*. *Parallel Processing Workshops (Auto-DASP 2017)*, 94–105, 2017.
- [8] S. Gaspers, J. Gudmundsson, M. Jones, J. Mestre, and S. Rümmele. *Turbocharging treewidth heuristics*. *International Symposium on Parameterized and Exact Computation (IPEC 2016)*, 13:1–13:13, 2016.

## Journal publications

- [9] T. M. Chan, S. Har-Peled, and M. Jones. *On locality-sensitive orderings and their applications. SIAM Journal on Computing*, 49(3): 583–600, 2020.
- [10] S. Har-Peled and M. Jones. *On separating points by lines*. *Discrete & Computational Geometry*, 63(3): 705–730, 2020.
- [11] S. Gaspers, J. Gudmundsson, M. Jones, J. Mestre, and S. Rümmele. *Turbocharging treewidth heuristics*. *Algorithmica*, 81(2): 439–475, 2019.
- [12] D. M. Budden and M. Jones. *Cautionary tales of inapproximability*. *Journal of Computational Biology*, 24(3): 213–216, 2017.
- [13] S. Canzar, K. M. Elbassioni, M. Jones, and J. Mestre. *Resolving conflicting predictions from multimapping reads*. *Journal of Computational Biology*, 23(3): 203–217, 2016.

# Current submissions & manuscripts

- [14] S. Har-Peled and M. Jones. Stabbing convex bodies with lines and flats. Submitted. 2020.
- [15] M. Jones. Cutting cycles of rods in space is FPT. 2020.

- [16] S. Har-Peled and M. Jones. Few cuts meet many point sets. Submitted. 2018.
- [17] M. Jones. *The maximum facility location problem*. Undergraduate honors thesis, University of Sydney. 2015.

#### TALKS

All listed talks below link to a PDF of the slides used (unless it was a whiteboard talk). Conference talks are typically twenty minutes, seminar talks are at least forty minutes.

## Conference & workshop talks

August 2020 · Some geometric applications of anti-chains [1], Canadian Conference on Computational Geometry (CCCG 2020), Online (due to COVID-19). Talk is also available on YouTube.

July 2020 · Active learning a convex body in low dimensions [2], International Colloquium on Automata, Languages and Programming (ICALP 2020), Online (due to COVID-19). Talk is also available on YouTube.

June 2020 · Fast algorithms for geometric consensuses [3], Symposium on Computational Geometry (SoCG 2020), Online (due to COVID-19). Talk is also available on YouTube.

Nov 2019 · Journey to the center of the point set [4], 70th Midwest Theory Day (MTD) at IIT, Chicago, IL, USA.

June 2019 · Journey to the center of the point set [4], Symposium on Computational Geometry (SoCG 2019), Portland, Oregon, USA.

June 2019 · Active learning a convex body in low dimensions [2], Young Researchers Forum (YRF), Symposium on Computational Geometry (SoCG 2019), Portland, Oregon, USA.

Jan 2019 · On locality-sensitive orderings and their applications [5], Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science (ITCS 2019), San Diego, California, USA.

Jan 2018 · On separating points by lines [6], Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA 2018), New Orleans, Louisiana, USA.

#### Seminar talks

Nov 2019 · Active learning a convex body in low dimensions [2], UIUC Theory CS Seminar, Illinois, USA.

Aug 2019 · On locality-sensitive orderings and their applications [5], Sydney algorithms group, New South Wales, Australia.

Sep 2018 · On locality-sensitive orderings and their applications [5], UIUC theory CS seminar, Illinois, USA.

Sep 2017 · On separating points by lines [6], UIUC theory CS seminar, Illinois, USA.

Oct 2016 · Turbocharging treewidth heuristics [8, 11], UIUC theory CS seminar, Illinois, USA.

Oct 2015 · The maximum facility location problem [13, 17], Sydney algorithms group, New South Wales, Australia.

#### **TEACHING**

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Fall 2019 · TA · CS473, Algorithms

Spr 2019 · Head TA · CS374, Intro to Algorithms & Models of Computation (†)

Fall 2017 · TA · CS473, Algorithms

(†): For that semester, ranked as an excellent teacher by students. Lists compiled by the University of Illinois Center for Innovation in Teaching & Learning.

University of Sydney, Australia 2016 · TA · COMP2022, Formal Languages & Logic

2015 · Head TA · COMP2007/2907, Algorithms & Complexity

2015 · TA · COMP2022, Formal Languages & Logic

2014 · TA · COMP2007/2907, Algorithms & Complexity

2014 · TA · COMP2022, Formal Languages & Logic

2014 · TA · INFO2120, Database Systems I

2013 · TA · INFO1105, Data Structures

#### EDITORIAL SERVICES

External Reviewer

Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (*SODA*): 2019, 2021 International Colloquium on Automata, Languages and Programming (*ICALP*): 2020 Foundations of Software Technology and Theoretical Computer Science (*FSTTCS*): 2018

Referee

Algorithmica (ALGO)

#### OUTREACH

2017–2020 CS Grad Ambassador

The role of a CS graduate ambassador is to connect with incoming graduate students. For example, meeting with them on visit days and answering any questions they have about the grad program or life at UIUC.

2015–2016 Zero Robotics mentor

For two years, I was a mentor for the Zero Robotics programming competition, when it was initially being piloted in Australia from September to December 2015. Each mentor was assigned a high school, where students would form a team and learn the necessary programming skills in order to control robots known as SPHERES. As a mentor, I visited a high school each week to help and teach the team of students the required programming, math, and physics in order to participate in the competition.

NCSS Challenge tutor

The NCSS challenge is a yearly programming competition for students in Australia and New Zealand. Students ranging from Years 7–12 are able to enter the Python programming competition. New problem sets are released each week, along with a set of notes explaining new concepts which help them solve the weekly problems. As a tutor, my responsibility was regularly helping students with any programming questions on an online forum.

#### NCSS Summer school tutor 2014

Every year, the NCSS summer school is a ten day summer school for students in Years 11 and 12. The school brings together talented high school students from Australia and New Zealand to participate in an intensive programming course. Each year, students learn the Python programming language and many other technologies such as HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and SQL. Throughout the period, students attend labs run by the tutors, and at the end form teams to build a final project (e.g., design and develop a new social networking site). As a tutor, my role was to run labs, help students with any programming questions, and organize fun activities for the students to enjoy.

#### **ACHIEVEMENTS & AWARDS**

2019	Mavis	Future	Faculty	Fellow	award	(MF <sub>3</sub> )	
------	-------	--------	---------	--------	-------	--------------------	--

The Allan Bromley Prize for best honours thesis 2015

> Award for first place in Advanced Data Models (COMP5338) Award for first place in Computational Geometry (COMP5045)

University of Sydney Academic Merit Prize

Dean's List of Excellence in Academic Performance University of Sydney, School of IT's High Honour Roll

Award for first place in Discrete Optimisation (COMP3530) 2014

University of Sydney Academic Merit Prize

Dean's List of Excellence in Academic Performance University of Sydney, School of IT's High Honour Roll

HEDLOC Undergraduate Prize for Algorithms 2013

University of Sydney Academic Merit Prize

Dean's List of Excellence in Academic Performance University of Sydney, School of IT's High Honour Roll

#### COMPUTER SKILLS

Primary languages C++, PYTHON, JAVA, LATEX.

HTML/CSS, JAVASCRIPT, SQL, MARKDOWN, GIT, CGAL. Experience with

PHP, C, C#. Previous experience with

Also previous experience with many other web technologies, including DJANGO, RUBY

ON RAILS, MONGODB, NEO4J, JQUERY, and BOOTSTRAP.